Preliminary Inventory of the Makerere University Slides, 1969
Hoover Institution Archives
- UGANDA.
  - SET III. THE GROWTH OF CHRISTIAN LEADERSHIP.
    - The other major reason for success was the faith of Msgr Streicher, seen here at the time of his jubilee in 1923 surrounded by the Ugandan priests he had ordained. Although progress was slow at first, it was steady, and the first Ugandan bishop, Bishop Joseph Kiwanuka, was consecrated in 1939., U34.
    - In the Anglican church, lay leadership has always been important. The Revival movement which began to affect Uganda in the 1930's was largely spread by teams of laymen, and one reason for its success would seem to be that it restored to the church the element of lay leadership which had been important in the early days, but had then suffered an eclipse. Blasio Kigozi, seen in this slide, was one of the men with whom the movement started., U35.
    - The 1960's have seen a new beginning made in the Anglican church to train women as church workers, and the widening of horizons for the Catholic sisters. Mother Vincent, seen here in Rome with His Holiness Pope Paul VI shortly after her election as Superior General of the Bannabikra, is one of an increasing number of sisters who have gone on to higher education or some form of specialised professional training either overseas or in Uganda, and who are trying to see that Ugandan Christian leaders are abreast of the times they live in., U36.
- KENYA.
  - SET I. THE EARLY DAYS.
    - Portuguese missionaries came to East as well as West Africa, though the shortness of effective Portuguese influence in East Africa meant that they accomplished Iless. Besides this, conditions were less favourable as Islam was strong among the Swahili peoples, and the Portuguese, like most Christians of their day, treated all Muslims as enemies. The only town with which the Portuguese were on friendly terms was Malindi. The pillar shown here, known as Vasco da Gama's Pillar, was until recently thought to be the original monument set up to mark Portuguese interests, but it is now known to be only a replica of the original., K1.
    - The 16th C was the period of strongest Portuguese domination of the coast, and this was due to the strength of Fort Jesus, built in 1593, captured by the Arabs in 1698. Inside it are the foundations of the church they built, which was destroyed and desecrated after the capture of the fortress. Fort Jesus was the site of the martyrdoms of a number of Portuguese and of Swahili converts, who were killed in 1631 by Yusuf bin Husain (Dom Jeronimo Chingulia) rather than become Muslims., K2.
    - Christian missionaries came to East Africa again somewhat by chance in 1844 when Dr. Ludwig Krapf, a Lutheran working with the Church Missionary Society, arrived trying to find an alternative route back to the Galla of Ethiopia. He decided, however, that it was God's will that he should remain in East Africa, and he established himself at Rabai, a few miles inland from Mombasa, where these remains of the Arab-style house built by him and by his companion, Rebmann, can still be seen., K3.
    - The church at Rabai is particularly associated with Johannes Rebmann, who worked here from 1846 - 1875, almost alone for the last 20 years of this time. Since all the churches built by the Portuguese have been destroyed, Rabai church is the oldest surviving church in Kenya, and is scheduled by the Kenya Government as a historical monument., K4.
    - Methodist missionaries arrived in Kenya in 1862, after reading Krapf's book about his missionary experiences. Wakefield, a pioneer Methodist, founded a station on the Tana River in 1884, but in a Masai raid the following year, the two missionaries and many local people, were killed. Wakefield remained in E.Africa for 27 years, and then became President of the United Methodist Free Churches in Britain., K5.
    - Lutheran missionaries also tried to begin work at Lamu, Witu and on the Tana River. This old Pokomo Christian from Ngao was converted by hese missionaries in the last century., K6.
    - Since the Lutheran missionaries were Germans, their work came to an end in the first World War, and was finally handed over to the Methodists. Ngao Church is on the edge of the Pokomo country, and is therefore now a Methodist church., K7.
    - The C.M.S. after 1875 concentrated their energies on Freretown, a settlement for freed slaves, just opposite Mombasa Island. The idea was to train those who lived in the settlement as evangelists, but this was largely unsuccessful. The missionaries were helped by two men, freed from illegal slave dhows by British warships, and brought up by the C.M.S. in Bombay, who returned to East Africa as adults, and were ordained as Anglican clergy. On their ordination, they signed the oaths of allegiance shown here. Like many freed-slaves in West Africa, they have taken European surnames., K8.
    - From 1895 onwards the missions at last began to make their up-country helped by the railway being built from Mombasa to Lake Victoria. Here is Stuart Watt, an independent missionary, and one of the first missionaries in Kikuyu and Kamba country. The picture represents the popular myth of the missionary, wearing a topee, sitting out of doors, and preaching. The only missing ingredients are the palmtree under which he should be sitting, and the rapt attention which should be on the hearers' faces. Until the advantages of the education offered by missions began to be seen, people were often hostile and suspicious of missions, and were only willing to send their children to school if they received financial compensation for the loss of their labour., K9.
    - Between 1898 and 1902 several missions entered Central Kenya - Presbyterians, the Africa Inland Mission, the C.M.S., the Gospel Missionary Society, the Holy Ghost Fathers, and the Consolata Mission. This picture shows Bishop Perlo who came to East Africa in 1902, was consecrated bishop in 1909, became Superior General of the Consolata Fathers in 1924, and died in 1948. He founded the Seminary for training African clergy in 1914., K10.
    - Western Kenya was entered from 1902 onwards, the Mill Hill Mission and the C.M.S. considering Kavirondo an extension of their Uganda work. The most powerful chief in this area was Mumia, Nabongo of Wanga, through whose headquarters the caravan routes to Uganda passed before the railway was built. He is seen in this photograph., K11.
    - For the most part, chiefs in Kenya were virtually non-existent until created by the British. Among those who came to power under colonial rule was Karoli, of Marang'a who gave permission for the building of Fort Hall, and, deciding that co-operation would profit his people more than resistance, asked for teachers. As a result the Consolata Fathers arrived. He was made a Paramount chief, and frequently visited the mission at Tuso, but not until his health began to fail in 1915 did he ask to join the catechumenate. He is seen here with his wife after their baptism. He died in 1916 aged about 70., K12.
  - SET II. A CHURCH ESTABLISHED.
    K1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 9: Rev. W.B. Anderson
    K10, 11: Consolata Mission
    K13, 17, 18, 20, 22: Rev. W. B. Anderson
    K14: C.M.S.
    K15, 16: Consolata Mission
    K21: Dr. D. Barrett
    K23, 24: East African Venture Co.
    - The missionary preaching to the heathen under a palm-tree was indeed a myth. As soon as a few converts had been won, the missions trained the most able of them as catechists. and they were the ones who made the initial contaot with their unconverted neighbours. Here is a group of the first C.M.S. teachers at Kahuhia in Central Kenya in c. 1906., K13.
    - A slightly different method was employed by the Rev. J.J. (later Bishop) Willis in Western Kenya. He opened a school at Maseno in 1906, and persuaded some of the Luo leaders to send their sons to it. During their holidays these boys then went and taught their own people. This is a `school photo' taken in 1906., K14.
    - Apart from the few men ordained on the coast, it was a long time before the first clergy were ordained. The Consolata Mission opened a seminary in 1914, this picture shows Fr. James Camisassa one of the first 2 Kenyan Catholic priests, celebrating his jubilee in 1952., K15.
    - The training of religions sisters was begun during the time of Bishop Perlo. The Mary Immaculate Sisters had their first beginnings in 1918, as a sodality. In 1929 the first temporary professions were made, and until 1948 they elected their own Superior General for the first time, Mother Guiseppa Mamboi., K16.
    - In 1952 when Mau Mau broke out, a number of Christians felt they could not take the oaths demanded of them because these were contrary to their profession of Christianity. An unknown number died rather than take the oaths. This decision must have been a very difficult one to make, since Mau Mau made demands for social justice which was being denied to the Kikuyu, but they would not agree to the violent methods or the type of oathing. The Anglican Cathedral at Marang'a is dedicated to their memory. Here we see one of the paintings by Elimo Njau which decorates its walls., K17.
    - During the Emergency, one factor which strengthened the Kikuyu Christians was the Revival Movement. This had spread from Uganda largely through teams of lay Christians, and led people to a deeper commitment to Christianity. This photograph is of a Revival Convention held in Western Kenya in 1961 which was attended by several thousand people., K18.
    - Bishop Festo Olang', Anglican bishop of Maseno, is here seen during the dedication of Butere Church. This is a large brick church, the entire cost of which was borne by the local congregation, and it can seet a thousand people., K19.
    - In Kenya there are more independent churches than anywhere else in East Africa, and they are of greater importance. They seem to spring in large part from a feeling of dissatisfaction about the failure of the mission churches either to give much responsibility to Africans under colonial rule. Some leaders of the strong Dini ya Israel church are seen here. This church started in Western Kenya in 1931. It shews Pentecostal characteristics and groups of JoIsrael dancing and singing down the road are a common sight in Western Kenya., K20.
    - A more recently established independent church is the Legio Maria Church, a break away from the Catholic Church which started among the Luo in 1960. At first it drew very large numbers of adherents but numbers are now said to be declining, and a further schism has occurred within it - both these developments are not infrequent in independent church movements. Another not unusual feature is that women play an important part in its leadership., K21.
    - Among the peoples of Central Kenya, independency seems to be less important than formerly, and since the gaining of political independence, there have been large numbers of people baptised into the other churches. This pictures shows a service at which adult converts are being received into the Presybterian Church: the Church elder in the picture has just seen his mother (kneeling) baptised., K22.
    - The grwoth of an African clergy had been slower in Kenya than elsewhere. But this slide shows that progress is being made. These two Kenyan Catholic bishops were consecrated by Pope Paul VI on his visit to Uganda in 1969., K23.
    - Target is a Christian newspaper published by the National Christian Council of Kenya, which has never been afraid to take a strong stand on social and political issues. When before the 1969 general elections tribal tension led to a renewal of oathing, Target strongly denounced this. This front page shows the crowds at the funeral of a lay-reader who lost his life when he refused to take those oaths., K24.
- TANZANIA
  - SET I. MISSIONARIES VERSUS SLAVERY.
    T4, 11: Rev. W.B. Anderson.
    T5, 6, 7, 9: Fr. F. Versteijnen and Holy Ghost Fathers.
    T8: Fr. J, Baur and Peramiho Publications.
    - Tipu Tip. Missions were first brought to Tanzania by accounts of the horrors of the slave trade, which had greatly increased during the 19th C. The most powerful Arab slave-trader was Tipu Tip. For many years he made Tabora his headquarters, and then moved Westwards into the Congo, where, bu 1875 he ruled over a large empire., T1.
    - Dr. David Livingstone, the missionary-traveller who did most to expose the slave-trade. His journey of 1855-6 took him to the Zambezi/Congo watershed, and through Malawi, and led directly to the founding of the Universities' Mission to Central Africa, and his later travels through Southern Tanzania, Malawi and the Western Congo. His concern was to open up paths for Christianity and commerce in order to defeat the slave-trade and bring Christianity and civilization to Africa., T2.
    - The main slave routes ran through Tanzania to Bagamoyo whence the slaves were taken to Zanzibar and sold in the slave-market pictured here. The U.M.C.A. arrived in Zanzibar in 1862, the Holy Ghost Fathers the following year, and both cared for freed and ransomed slaves., T3.
    - The U.M.C.A. `s settlement was at Mbweni on the island of Zanzibar, and the ruins of some of the little stone houses where the people were settled are shown here., T4.
    - In 1868 The Holy Ghost Fathers moved to the mainland, securing a grant of land at Bagamoyo. This picture shows the deed of transfer., T5.
    - This is a map of the freedom village at Bagamoyo. Both the U.M.C.A. and the Holy Ghost Fathers educated those who were settled at the mission, hoping that they would then become evangelists to their own people, so helping to open up the interior, as the Sierra Leonians had done on the West Coast., T6.
    - This is a page from the register of those who gained their freedom and were settled at the mission. The most intelligent were given an academic education; those less able were trained as artisans; and these who shewed little ability worked on the well-run mission plantations., T7.
    - This picture shows a crowd of people outside the old church at Bagamoyo. It was built of coral blocks by the Christian freed slaves, and when in 1873 Livingstone's body was carried down to the coast by his African followers, it was laid overnight in Bagamoyo church before being taken to England for burial., T8.
    - Most of those who came under the care of the missions received Christian instruction and were baptised. This is a page from the Bagamoyo baptism register. When old enough, the boys and girls were married off, and settled in Christian villages situated around Bagamoyo. It was hoped that these would prove attractive to the surrounding Muslim and pagan population, but they were too strictly run, and eventually the missions found a better method of approach was through the establishment of a wide network of bush schools., T9.
    - Msgr. Allgeyer was Vicar-Apostolic of Zanguebar (Zanzibar) from 1896-1912, and was responsible for beginning many new mission stations and catechist's posts, and of pushing ahead with the establishment of schools. He also brought sisters into the Vicariate to work in educating girls. He retired because of ill-health in 1912., T10.
    - The U.M.C.A. were able to acquire the site of the slave-market on Zanzimbar after the suppression of the slave trade in 1873, and on the site they built this fine cathedral, whose high alter stands on the spot where previously the whipping post had been., T11.
    - Probably because they did not demand celibacy, nor such high educational standards as the Catholics, the Anglicans had an earlier success in ordaining Africans. One of the early African priests was Yohan Abdullah, ordained priest in March 1898. The oath of allegiance to the Bishop which he signed at his ordination is reproduced here., T12.
  - SET II. THE MOVE INLAND.
    T13: U.M.C.A.
    T16, 22, 24: White Fathers.
    T17: C.M.S.
    T20: Moravian Church in Tanzania.
    T21: Fr. John Baur and Peramiho Publications.
    T25: White Fathers and Ntungamo Seminary.
    - In 1876, Bishop Steere of the U.M.C.A. shewn here, tried to lead a party of ex-slaves back to the area of Malawi whence they had originally been captured. All were Christians or catechumens. But the hardships of the journey proved discouraging, and when, on reaching Masasi, they found themselves in more fertile country where food could be more easily obtained, they refused to go further. Their settlement was the beginning of the present Anglican Diecese of Masasi. Bishop Steere was a great Swahili scholar, and did much for the study of that language., T13.
    - A second U.M.C.A. station on the mainland of Tanzania which was permanently occupied at the same time as Masasi was begun was Magila, in Bondei country. This had the alternative name of Msalabani, the place of the cross, since when Dr. Drapf had visited the area years before, and preached, he had cut a cross into the bark of a tree to mark the spot, and this could still be seen. The stone church seen here is dedicated to the Holy Cross and was completed in 1886., T14.
    - This picture shows Kageye, on the southern shores of L. Victoria, also reached by missionaries in 1876. The missions bound for Uganda had to pass through Tanzania, and this led to the opening up of the interior much faster than would otherwise have been the place. Two graves can still be seen at Kageye, just beyond these mango trees: one is the graves of Frederick Burke who accompanied H.M.Stanley in 1875 and died here; the second is the grave of Dr. John Smith, one of the first party of C.M.S. missionaries to Uganda who died before reaching his destination., T15.
    - Kamoga, or Bukumbi, near Mwanza was the first mission founded by the White Fathers on the southern Lake shore. It was founded in 1882 when the White Fathers temporarily evacuated Uganda. The building of the first church is seen in progress here, but this has since been replaced. Although the White Fathers returned to Uganda in 1884, this mission in Tanzania remained also., T16.
    - The C.M.S. also had a mission on the southern lake shore, but because of numerous deaths and much sickness, it was moved several times, being finally located at Nassa. This picture shows Daudi Mbasa, one of the first Sukuma converts, teaching a class to read. The Sukuma were very unresponsive to Christianity at first, and it was not until Baganda evangelists arrived in 1891, among them Nathaniel Mudeka (later to be ordained, and to be the senior African clergyman in Uganda) that the first converts were made., T17.
    - German colonial authority was formalised between 1885 and 1890, and large bomas were built. This is the boma at Bagamoyo. The annexation by Germany led to the arrival of several German missionary societies:Lutherans, Moravians, and a new group of Catholic missionaries, the Benedictines., T18.
    - A group of Lutheran missionaries began work at the northern end of L.Malawi, spreading east and north-east from that base. This little Lutheran church is at a place they named Pommern, a few miles south of Iringa., T19.
    - The Moravians began work in almost the same area, but agreed to extend northwards and westwards so as not to come into conflict with the Lutheran Mission. This map shows the present extension of their work between L.Malawi and Tabora. They occupied Urambo, originally a station of the London Missionary Society, in 1897, and later occupied the intervening country of Ukimbu, but this work was hardly established before the first World War., T20.
    - Bishop Cassian Spiss and Mwalimu Kaver. The imposition of German rule not only brought new missions to Tanzania, but also provoked strong African resistance, culminating in the Maji Maji Rising of 1905-7, and all mission work suffered during the general disruption of this period. The work most affected was that of the Benedictine mission. Several missionaries lost their lives when they ignored warnings that it was dangerous to travel. Besides Bishop Spiss pictured here, two Sisters and two Brothers were killed, and also the catechist, Mwalimu Xaver., T21.
    - In north-western Tanzania, the White Fathers founded the station of Ushirombo in 1891, and extended their work from there. This old mission has scarcely been altered since it was built, and water is still drawn from a well in the cloister. A minor seminary was begun here early in the century, and this picture, dating from 1909 shows seminarians mending their clothes. This mission was attacked not long after its founding, and part of the surrounding defensive wall can be seen in this photograph., T22.
    - In Buhaya the White Fathers began work at Kashozi, a few miles from Bukoba in 1892. Like Bukumbi, this mission was begun when the White Fathers had to leave Uganda temporarily after the Battle of Mengo, but once founded, it remained permanently. It was also called Marienberg, and the church, here seen in building, is still in use today., T23.
    - Dr. Adrien Atiman worked for over 60 years as a missionary with the White Fathers. Originally enslaved in West Africa, he was freed in North Africa by the mission, and trained as a doctor-catechist at the Institute founded by Cardinal Lavigerie in Malta, and in 1888 came to start work in Tanzania. He spent most of his working life at Karema (S.W.Tanzania), and received decorations from several nations for his work. His son, seen here with him, became a priest. He died in 1965., T24.
  - SET III. THE CHURCH GROWS TO MATURITY.
    T25, 26: U.M.C.A.
    T27, 28: White Fathers
    T33, 36: Fr J. Baur and Peramiho Publications.
    T34: East African Venture Co (Target and Lengo)
    T35: Tanzania Ministry of Information
    - Bishop Frank Weston, bishop of Zanzibar from 1908 to 1924, did much to encourage the development of African clergy in the Anglican Church, and to give them real responsibility. His episcopacy also saw the establishment of The Community of the Sacred Passion, an order of Anglican missionary sisters who work with the U.M.C.A. and an African Sisterhood followed. By the time of Weston's death, African clergy outnumbered missionaries., T25.
    - The first men from the Masasi area were ordained priests in 1922. In 1926 Masasi became a diocese with Bishop Vincent Lucas as its first bishop. He also did much to encourage vocations, and St. Cyprian's college was founded in 1929. The first deacons, seen here with Bishop Lucas, were ordained in 1932., T26.
    - Congregations of African sisters were started in many areas in Tanzania. White Sisters are here teaching sewing to novices and postulants at Tabora in 1920., T27.
    - By now African sisters outnumber missionary sisters (1969 expatriates totalled 829; indigenous sister 1408). This picture shews a noviciate at Tabora. Sisters are engaged in many forms of social work; in nursing and teaching, and in catechetical work, and an increasing number receive some form of higher education or professional training. Most congregations are now independent and elect their own Superior General., T28.
    - The great size of Tanzania means that missions were slow to occupy all areas. This map shews the distribution of Protestant missions by 1914. Central Tanzania is relatively thinly populated, and the greatest concentrations, of populations are on the borders of the country. The government did not want competition between missions (though this could not always be avoided, and tried to keep the missions confined to separate area. By 1914 some areas were therefore wholly Catholic, others wholly Protestant. It will also be seen that at this stage different Protestant missions did not compete with one another as they did in Kenya., T29.